what's up everybody welcome back to 55
minute physiology in today's episode
we're finally gonna do it we're taking
the plunge folks we're going to talk
about calories I can't go a single day
without seeing something on social media
about people arguing back and forth
about how calories are the only thing
that matter or that they don't matter at
all and really to be honest I'd say it
frustrates to me but it doesn't because
I don't even care it's so bad people
have such a fundamental lack of
understanding of what's really going on
I finally decided let's make a video we
will walk people through the very basics
of calories what they really are what
matters particularly in respect to
energy balance so where this
conversation comes most into play is in
other words do I need to cut calories to
lose weight yes or no are there some
other mechanisms or gain muscle for that
matter and I think what you're gonna
find here is even though we're covering
the basics the vast majority of people
this includes PhDs nutritionists experts
in the field don't understand the very
very fundamental concepts that I'm about
to lay out to today it's honestly not
that complicated
I blows my mind how people don't
understand these basics it really shocks
me alright so we're gonna have some
interesting conversations and I think if
we do this and we spread this message
and this basic information gets out then
I think we can have some very
interesting and very important
conversations about food because it does
extend far beyond just calories but we
can't get there unless we can have some
basic agreement about what's going on
with calories with quality with quantity
and we can throw away the zealots and
the people on the on the extremes so
let's tackle it let's jump right in
energy balance quality versus quantity
and the great calorie debate well well
you first have to recognize is whenever
someone puts you in this position or ask
you the question of what's more
important calories or quantity or
quality the first thing I want you to
understand is this is by definition a
false dilemma this is what we call in
logic a fallacy of black and white there
is no such thing it's not one or the
other I'm not I'm not sure
when people think that it has to be
quality or has to be quantity its
obviously both whether we're talking
about eating for performance muscle gain
fat loss health longevity it's a
combination of both clearly you can't
have high quality food and totally
mismatch calories I'm not gonna name
names here but there are some people
that get a lot of attention
who will purport the idea that literally
calories don't matter and I've heard
people on very prominent podcasts get
cornered with this and the host will
graciously give them an out to say
things like well surely if you gain if
you ate fifteen thousand calories a day
of this food that you say is magical you
would gain weight and then proponents
say no no you still wouldn't I'm telling
you you wouldn't and that's utterly
ridiculous there's some point where
calories matter the flip side of the
equation
just because you count all your calories
and line them up and you eat crap food
all day you're not going to be in good
health performance recovery standing so
the obvious answer here is let's just
stop the conversation about what's more
important and realize that both of them
have a very significant role so that's
our first step in understanding what's
going on with this calorie debate and I
can give you a couple of very practical
examples this is my friend Tori and and
she asked me to come to one of her gyms
that she was working out with a couple
of years ago and one of her friends was
in the audience in there and they were
asking me about calories and she her
friend had lost
bless her heart fifty or sixty pounds or
something over the year or two before
and I said great what was your approach
and she said I didn't pay attention to
anything except eating the highest
quality foods I could and I said
fantastic that's amazing that's a win
for everybody right listen then I said
well what's your question that sounds
like you're doing great and she said
well really
I've been stalled for two or three
months and I haven't lost any weight and
that amount of time and so my response
was well have you started eating less
food and she looked at me like with
complete bewilderment well what do you
mean if quality is the only thing that
matters and then it hit her like a
lightbulb oh
of course quantity matters at some point
right
so in her particular case maybe it was
best for her to start by just focusing
only on quality but at some point folks
quantity does start to matter and we can
have a good conversation later in a
separate point about what's better to
start people focus on quantity or
quality but we do have to recognize both
matter in our particular case all the
best quality of food is not gonna have
you get to a negative caloric balance
which is what you have to have as we'll
see in a second to lose weight
eventually you're gonna have to bring
those calories down and the opposite in
that equation the hair is this is my
friend Lauren and she came out and
worked in my lab for a summer and she's
actually here right now and she told me
a wonderful story of herself and she
said I could use this and by that I mean
I didn't ask her at all and I'm just
totally throwing her out there she
doesn't really have social media but if
you see her find her when you make sure
they make fun of her and let her know
that I'm that I brought her up in my
video but Lauren told me that you know
she went through the same problem where
she ate a whole bunch of calories and
she thought quality is the only thing
that mattered and so she thought she
could eat in excess just any foe didn't
matter as long as it was high-quality
food you know fresh vegetables and and
food and in non processed food and she
gained a ton of weight and so what she
had to also realizes yeah you know what
you can live for the most part getting
away with it if you're focusing on
quality foods relative the less quality
foods you have a bigger buffer but that
buffer is not limitless it does start to
matter at some point so make sure you're
being cognizant that calories do count
and so I love this physics joke you
probably won't care for it and you can
pause the screen I'm not gonna go to the
whole thing in detail but it basically
says something like this that the
traditional view of weight loss says
that there's a certain amount of
calories in certain amount of energy
expenditure out and if you have more
calories in than out there's a net
energy gain in opposition to that if you
have less calories in and/or more
calories going out then you have a net
energy loss but then for some reason we
think that there's this revolutionary
new diet to where you can add more
calories in no calories out and that
somehow the calories will
in this anomaly of space-time continuum
or something like that so I don't know
how that exactly works to people you're
gonna hear the argument of an open
versus a closed system I get all that
but you're really missing the boat and
to be honest with you it doesn't matter
hopefully what I'm gonna lay out to you
in the next few minutes is this is not
the right conversation it's utterly
unimportant we're having the physics
conversation about something that is
really very clear calories do matter
they're not the only part of the
equation but they do matter so who cares
about this it's really not that
important what I'm really getting at
here is this point whether someone comes
to you or you go to your client with a
quality is most important approach or
you go with a quantity is most important
approach either one of those are just a
system to help you get to the same place
which is what we call a desired energy
balance and this is what's really most
about for this context again this is
where if somebody who's trying to gain
muscle or lose fat you've got to get
them in the proper energy balance so you
can use a combination of emphasizing
quality or emphasizing quantity whatever
you want they're both just different
systems aimed at getting you to the same
thing now most people can see this from
the quantitative perspective right
obviously if I'm focusing on quantity
that's getting me directly to energy
balance but the real loss of
conversation or the confusion here
happens with the qualitative how is it
that emphasizing quality only works if
it's all about balance we hear this all
the time right well I didn't figure at
all I didn't count calories I went up
and maybe calories and maybe you could
document that you went way up in
calories but yet you lost weight
if calories are the only thing that
counted how is that physically possible
and they think that's proof that they're
right well what people don't realize is
the next 15 or 20 minutes here I'll show
you how if you emphasize quality
oftentimes that leads you into a proper
energy balance so in either case it
still is about energy balance it's just
different ways to get there
so let's talk for quite a few minutes
here about how calorie counting works
now in general it doesn't work very well
for a bunch of different reasons and the
first one is adherence right now keep in
mind see how the word there general is
underlined I'm not saying it doesn't
work because I'm gonna get a thousand
comments from people that says I counted
calories and I lost 100 pounds or I've
kept it fine there are actually a huge
amount of people in this part on this
planet that were just fine counting
calories in fact point number one is
adherence so counting calories can be
effective but the reason that jelly
doesn't work is it's very hard to do
you've got a track and away and measure
things and you've got to be very
judicious about that that works for some
people in fact if you want to listen to
my podcast the body of knowledge that's
up on stitcher and iTunes the body of
knowledge com go to season one chapter
one point six I talked in there about
how I like to categorize people it's
different personality types I also
talked about this on the Joe Rogan
podcast when I was on there and I
actually labeled people as cooks bakers
and chefs and you can watch those
episodes of that podcast to hear more
about that but some people do do very
well with a detailed plan that includes
tracking weighing measuring if that's
one of you fantastic I would encourage
you to try calorie counting and tracking
it can work fine its millions of people
have lost millions of pounds doing it
having said that a lot of other people
don't do very well on it and so one of
the major reasons why people would then
think hey calories don't matter is
because I tried a calorie counting diet
and it failed but that's not actually
meaning the diet the physics and the
chemistry is not true it just means it
didn't work for the adherence which is a
very legitimate conversation it's just
not does it mean the calories don't
count so the second one is accuracy and
the third one is that some calories have
an influence on behavior and so let's
talk a little bit more about those next
two starting with the accuracy so the
first reason why calorie counting well
again this is whether you're trying to
go up and you're like I'm having
hanging muscle of of increased calories
or you're trying to use it to lose fat
it's really the same conversation it's
about manipulating calories all right so
how do you know how many calories to
consume the only way to really do that
is to go through some type of assessment
and there's a bunch of different ways
you can do that
but in order to get there you have to
understand one fundamental concept is
the total amount of energy that you use
in other words the total energy
expenditure t'ee it's a combination of
three things really three major
categories number one your resting
metabolic rate you may have also heard
this referred to as basal metabolic rate
now those are not the same exact thing
but for our purposes here they're close
enough so it's your resting metabolic
rate plus what's called your exercise
activity thermogenesis in other words
how many calories you burn through
exercise and the last category is your
non EA T so your non-exercise activity
thermogenesis now if you add up resting
metabolic rate eat and meat that's gonna
tell me how many calories you're burning
so how many calories you're burning to
just be alive resting metabolic rate
this is to run your immune system to
pump your blood to grow hair all the
things your body has to do to minimally
survive plus how many calories you burn
from working out and how many calories
you burn from non exercising physical
activity you add all that stuff up and
you understand how many calories you get
well in order to and then no resting
metabolic rate eat and meat you have to
have some sort of assessment and you
have a bunch of different options here
I'll start actually at the bottom of
number four I think honestly the best
metric the best way to assess here
especially for fat loss is test-retest
in other words are you tracking and
weighing your body composition if you're
doing that who cares about what your
calorie prescription is at right so what
I honestly do most of the time is okay
track and weigh your your weight let's
make sure we're not losing all muscle
mass if it's weight loss and over the
course of several months are you having
an adequate balance of are you not too
hungry all the time
to be hungry yeah I'm very often at all
are you losing weight are you still
feeling recovered are you sacrificing
sleep quality anything like that because
if you were like hey I'm satiated
I feel fine I'm not feeling like I'm
restricted I'm losing weight at the
appropriate rate I'm feeling recovered
and not having any problems and that's a
perfect caloric assessment if you're all
those things are going well but you're
not losing weight then we maybe have to
lower calories or if you're losing a ton
of weight but it's coming at the cost of
recovery your sleep or motivation or
something like that then maybe we need
both calories back up all right but the
other approach moving sort of up the
ladder and which i think is equally
unfeasible is some sort of a laboratory
assessment I will talk about that sort
of quickly what most people do actually
is number three which is get some sort
of estimate so you can look anywhere
online or text books or studies and you
can get things and say hey here based on
your age height weight here's how you
would estimate how your BMR or your arm
are and here's how you could estimate
your physical activity you can see that
of course on something like a treadmill
or an elliptical that'll tell you hey
here's your estimated calories you're
burning recognize folks those are
tremendously inaccurate even and if you
know anything about me you know my
stance on the actual trackers the apps
on your phone things like that are
horrendously bad with accuracy but these
are all your different approaches so
going back to laboratory one this is
what you would actually have to do to
honestly know how your total energy
expenditure so you can see in the
picture over here with the lady laying
down she's actually getting her basal
metabolic or resting metabolic rate
assessed so you have to lay in a
laboratory with the big hood over your
face and I have all of the calories
you're burning inhaling and exhaling
measured for a couple of hours and this
would give you a pretty good indication
of your basal metabolic rate you would
have to also then have to be like the
gentleman on the right and where that
thing portably and those units cost
about $30,000 each you have to wear that
when you're doing your physical activity
and your exercise you'd have to wear
that all day that's the only real way to
know exactly how many calories you're
burning and so it's pretty
practical and unfeasible for most people
this is why they generated these
prediction equations that are they're
okay for a big you know three hundred
fifty million people at a time but for
the individual person it's pretty
inaccurate other things you can do in
terms of assessment are things like diet
recalls so there could be a 24-hour
48-hour recall so in other words you
look back and you guys say okay how much
did I eat yesterday today and you kind
of list everything due and you usually
you upload that to some website that'll
give you a breakdown of how many
calories you consume or your physical
activity and things like that and
there's some benefit here lights just
like anything else but there's also some
potential problems
number one is honesty people aren't
necessarily always forthright with
exactly what they ate and how much
memory is a problem of course sometimes
you don't remember exactly what you ate
in the last 48 hours knowledge is a big
difficulty especially people who are not
in this field of portion size so people
don't know what three ounces really
looked like they don't know what a pound
was or six milliliters they're really
guess and if they're off by more than
five or 10% then everything's out of
whack anyways because that's how much
you're trying to adjust calories for the
most part as you go there are several
studies now that have shown that people
that are obese tend to underestimate
their portion sizes by about 50% when
they report and this is the population
we're probably most trying to help and
they're the ones that are the most
inaccurate with their portion knowledge
for the most part there are also other
consideration what happens if you did a
diet recall in a very atypical day and
it's gonna throw all your numbers in
your equations off we also have some
evidence to suggest the people who have
a lower education also have a more
inaccurate or worse response and so you
can use a recall but there's all kinds
of problem there I actually encourage
people to use this this is the NIH Kevin
Hall I think put this together and it's
it's a website that you can use and it's
free where you can track a lot of your
metrics now anyone that's ever done any
tracking before are you're probably
rolling your eyes right now I understand
because we're I feel like for 10 or 50
years there were online trackers for
caloric estimations and they were just
terrible and they didn't evolve at all
at all this one is completely different
I promise you you can go to the body
weight planner google nih body weight
planet err it is way different than
anything that's ever been out there and
I think it's actually extremely good it
allows you to have a lot of manipulation
of different things really personalized
individualized and it is by far the most
accurate thing I've seen the most usable
thing for especially for
individualization so I'm showing you the
front screen right here and you're
probably looking at again being like
I've seen this a thousand times but I'm
telling you a lot more goes into it than
just this front screen I just didn't
want to show you all of it so you can
use an app like that or a thousand
different apps if you prefer one over
the other it's really up to you but this
is really how you would would track it
so the obvious question then and I've
sort of alluded to some of these answers
a couple of times of which of these
things are the best and if you've ever
had a class for me or seen many of these
videos you know the answer is it depends
you're gonna have to understand the
context of the situation so if you're
working with somebody I think it's very
rare that you really need to go to step
number one here getting in a laboratory
and have a 24 hour assessment is
probably very unlikely to be needed you
might be able to get away with a
three-day food tracker upload it to
Kevin Hall system there and that might
be good enough maybe you want to go more
extensive or maybe even an estimates
good enough all right this is up for you
to decide depending on the context the
situation how important knowing calories
really are for your situation so that's
what you would really do to assess it
you also have to keep in mind this
factor and this is what makes things
even more difficult so at the top you
can see that equation again so t'ee
which is your total energy expenditure
equals that resting metabolic rate eaten
eat but keep in mind a couple of things
either the thermal effect of food which
is that TEF is a function or a part of
that resting metabolic rate and as we'll
see in a second here that changes
depending on what you eat therefore your
resting metabolic rate
is quite often by the hour actually
depending on when you're eating now your
resting metabolic rate generally
accounts for about 50 to 60 percent of
your te E and it is pretty variable
there and it depends but it's a big big
big chunk of your total energy
expenditure your eat in other words your
exercise calories has a tremendous
variability well because a lot of people
are contact assigns some people exercise
really really hard so it can be 10 to 30
percent of your total caloric
expenditure as well but the real big one
is neat and this is the one that really
has changed our view of how calories
work in the last 20 years or so once we
started to realize that you're neat
which is your physical activity this is
what I call it right so exercise is
exercise but things like walking
gardening doing the dishes having sex
with your partner all that is not really
exercise it's more like physical
activity but it can count for a
significant amount of weight management
fidgeting also so those either like tap
your feet or your waist kind of moving
around that burns actually a significant
amount of calories throughout the day
standing versus walking so those of you
that have heard things like how can
standing help you know having a standing
desk helped me lose weight it'll
actually add a couple of calories per
hour that builds out throughout a day
throughout a week throughout a month
throughout a year that adds two sub to
be several pounds and so the note I put
at the bottom there the knee can
actually add up doing it or remove an
additional hundred and 150 extra cake
house per hour for some people and the
reason I have it highlighted is because
the vast majority of the research is
going the direction is saying neat is
the real thing that causes somebody to
have a hard time gaining weight or have
a hard time losing weight this seems to
be the really big variable it's also
something you have a tremendous ability
to to play with and you can influence it
heavily by doing things like just being
more active walking more standing desks
or fidget desks or things like that
as I mentioned here though this has
really high personal intra and
interpersonal 'ti and a lot of different
things influences is not the same every
single day a lot of these numbers change
with your mood your environment your
sleep what the temperature is outside
you can induce some shivering if you're
a little bit cold this is some of the
research that I showed setting the
thermostat in your house down a few
degrees can actually lead to substantial
fat loss over the course of a couple of
months just being a little bit colder
because it influences neat how's it go
up just a few percentage points as you
start losing weight you also have to
realize you have to adjust caloric
prescription because you have a bunch of
different things that happen number one
the thermal effect of food goes down as
you start losing late because you stop
eating as much alright so the thermal
effect the food is the energy that you
burn breaking down food in your stomach
well if you're eating less food you're
going through less than a little
effective food you're going through less
TEF resting metabolic rate is then
coming down neat also goes down but
tension to conserve and so this is what
I'll talk about in a few slides from now
but you sort of have something that
you're fighting here as you lower the
calories you eat there is some theory
here that your body will match that by
lowering it's neat to keep you conserve
that of body weight and this is the way
if somebody who's ever really crashed
down on calories and then it didn't work
and you went down harder in calories and
didn't working with down harder in
calories you're like I'm not worth
losing any weight therefore calories
don't matter no they totally matter your
body's just compensating for your lack
of ingesting calories by reducing its
caloric expenditure and you're like no
no I kept my exercise is saying well you
might have but your body might have just
throttled way down on me the neat but
just really happens very often I'll tell
you a story about that happening to one
of my athletes here in a second the
third thing you have to consider is
resting metabolic rate goes down just
from a fact of being smaller and this is
really dependent on what you're actually
losing so if you're losing fat you're
resting
Bhalla crate won't go down that much if
you're losing muscle it'll go down a
little bit more now it's not a huge
number but it is a number and that does
start to matter forth eat goes down
right so smaller people burn less
calories for exercise so as you're now a
smaller person that same exact exercise
about doesn't burn as many calories and
then lastly you really have to consider
what you're losing so you've lost some
weight now but where did that weight
come from fat water calories all those
play a factor as well so that's
something you have to consider that even
though maybe you started off on a diet
where you're measuring calories it was
working I know that's not working
anymore we have to realize these factors
are playing into the conversation and
the calculation as well so here's an
example of what I was talking about just
a second ago now this paper made waves a
couple of years ago and before I talk
about it I want to make sure we add some
caveats here this is not widely accepted
by the scientific community yet in fact
there's there's a lot of questioning
what's going on here it's really more of
a concept that it is extremely known and
what what Pontz are the author's point
here was is there's potentially an
evolutionary advantage to actually
countering a caloric deficit with a
caloric restriction of meat so in other
words if you reduce your or if you
reduce your calorie intake by 300
calories your body might reduce its need
by 300 calories to keep your make sure
your total energy expenditure is the
same or the same with exercise if you
burn an extra 300 calories with exercise
your body might match it a reducing me
by 300 to keep you at the same total
energy expenditure and I mean from an
evolutionary perspective in theory at
least this would keep you alive so this
is a fun experiment and as I mentioned
it's not a widely accept anything but it
does highlight the fact that this can
happen sometimes when you reduce
calories especially if you reduce them
to low for too far I think I spoke about
this on
Joe Rogan's podcast I was fortunate
enough to work with were Olympic gold
medalist and three-time defending world
champion now Helen marilla's and this is
what happened to her prior to making way
for the Rio Olympics is really
restricted for a long time kept lowering
calories and body weight just wasn't
changing we eventually went way up in
calories and all of a sudden body start
caming body weight started falling off
now that was not proof that calories
don't matter it was proof that something
like this happens and that your intake
in your ex take or your expenditure are
not just stale factors they're mosaic
and they're influenced by a lot of
different things another concept similar
to that is a kind of commentary now this
is not original data this is a
commentary about debunking the myth that
exercise is an effective weight loss
treatment now keep in mind here they are
not saying you don't need to exercise
for weight loss what they're simply
talking about is the calorie portion of
it in other words don't think you're
going to lose weight because you're
burning more calories from exercise
you're gonna lose that equation and I'll
explain I'll explain that in a second
and there's a thousand trillion billion
reasons why you need to exercise for
your health longevity your physical
performance and a million other reasons
and absolutely exercise is a critical
portion of any weight loss and obviously
of any muscle gain diet what they're
simply saying here is is not a very good
way to manipulate calories for the sake
of weight loss that's the argument and
that is pretty well-established they're
actually right there and so I'll give
you some examples here you can see the
foods on the left and how many calories
that are actually in them well people
are extremely distorted in their
understanding or view of how many
calories they burn with exercise and
that is a lot of times because you're
being marketed to like that so a company
that wants to sell their gym or their or
their especially their group exercise
class it's gonna tell you things like
hey our class burns a thousand calories
today you brought a thousand calories as
workout well that's extremely unlikely
more likely gonna burn two or three
hundred calories in an hour-long
exercise about and so you can see in the
slide here some of the equations so you
know you had that extra Cinnabon that
might take you an hour of aerobics class
to burn off right you have that
extra-large fly fry you might have to
hop on the rower for an hour and a half
so it's completely unreasonable to think
that you can out exercise eating too
many calories again
exercise is critical for some other
reasons we don't have time to get into
but it's not going to be the thing that
leads you to that energy deficit you're
looking for especially if you know
you're a college kid or otherwise and
maybe on a random Friday night you go
out for a couple of cokes and you know
not like you would add anything to that
coke like rum or vodka or anything right
making the calories go up any higher and
since you're a responsible young adult
you only have two or three right you
wouldn't have ten or twelve and then
since you're responsible and you didn't
have ten and twelve you wouldn't go home
and then add a whole thing of easy Mack
dinner have some extra fries and not
just on top of that right no of course
you wouldn't do that and you wouldn't do
that every single Friday in those
Saturday nights right so you wonder why
it's hard to lose weight the calories
add up really really really fast you
couldn't have a night like that and then
think oh man I had a terrible night last
night
oh don't worry though I'm gonna go train
really hard tomorrow you'll never catch
up to that 2,000 calories not even close
so it's just a lot better than 92 junk
in the first place for the sake of
managing calories or energy deficit or
surplus the other thing also is this
should help you understand that you
should not eat for a reward so do not
fall into the trap of saying like oh I
had a great workout I burned 800
calories therefore I'm gonna go reward
myself with pizza tonight you're gonna
crush past 800 calories for 200 calories
or whatever it is really really really
fast another thing to keep in mind let's
say you did burn 800 calories in a hard
workout that doesn't mean you're at an
8-under calorie deficit because remember
if it took you an hour to burn
and in her calories in a hard workout
you wouldn't burn zero calories in that
hour sitting on the couch you still have
basal metabolic rate right
you're burning some calories maybe it's
50 calories sitting on the couch maybe
it's 100 I don't know it said something
right so really what you have to do is
take however many calories you burn from
your exercise - not by how many you
would have burned in that same time
sitting there that's your deficit so in
this case maybe it's not a hundred
calorie deficit maybe it's six our
calorie deficit this stuff starts to
matter over time if you're miss
calibrating by a couple of hundred
calories right okay so that covers for
the most part the accuracy stuff as I
mentioned this is one of the reasons why
calorie counting in this case maybe
isn't the best because so many factors
go into it it ends up being a wild guess
right it's really off depending on the
person and all the other factors one
thing I haven't touched on yet is food
labeling what you don't realize food
labels can be off by 10 maybe a little
15 percent so this is really problematic
if you think you're having a 500 calorie
meal and it's actually 550 calories or
450 calories or less and so it's really
difficult because we're not very
standardized in that and some companies
are even worse than that 10 or 15%
marker we've talked about user error a
lot people have a really hard time
understanding and tracking what's
actually they're really consuming
especially if they're not using a scale
but I think the one that surprises
people the most and this is probably the
part of the video where you're gonna go
oh my god I can't believe nobody
explained this to me ever before all of
these things you've heard and all these
arguments are gonna make a lot more
sense when you hear these next two final
points in fact I don't understand why
this is not the beginning of the
conversation every time this topic comes
up because it seems like people who
argue that calories don't matter at all
don't have the faintest clue of these
last two points and that blows me away
how you could have a PhD or write books
in this field and not understand the
next two points so here's the argument
right
so people say all right well if all
calories are equal and all that matters
is energy balance how is it you're you
really gonna try to say that for example
a half a cup of Crisco which would be a
thousand calories is equal to a thousand
calories which would be 20 cups of
carrots no of course not
and then they was a hot that's proof
calories don't count don't matter no
that's proof you don't understand basic
physiology and basic chemistry that's
not at all how it works obviously a
thousand calories of carrots is far
better for you for weight management sup
then 1/2 a cup of highly processed
crappy calories in Crisco right so
what's the difference here well it comes
down to a couple of things number one
caloric in sorption now caloric
absorption is not really the right idea
and the right word really when it comes
down to is composition and thermal
effective food and then say tidy or say
TV the the sensation of filling full
so here's really what happens then you
have to realize that a portion of the
calories you ingest can be lost into
non-digestible fiber so if you want you
can go back and watch some of the other
videos when I've explained to you what
carbohydrates really are and so a
portion of carbohydrates are fiber
that's right fiber is a carbohydrate so
if you had a thousand calories of
carrots you would acknowledge there's a
lot of fiber and carrots are in fruits
and vegetables not a lot of fiber in
Crisco so of those thousand calories
let's say and I'm making these numbers
up it doesn't matter at all the scale
really doesn't matter if I'm way off
it's going to highlight the same point
so of those thousand say there were 50
grams of fiber and you know that there's
4 calories per gram of carbohydrate so
of those thousand two hundred are
actually fiber now some fiber you can
digest then you'll absorb just fine some
of it you can't and it actually just
goes through your system and this is why
fiber helps us defecate right so I'll
just call it 5050 so half of those fiber
digestible half or not again that's not
really
but you get the idea so what that really
means is since there's 200 calories of
that 1000 or fiber and of that 200 100
into the Mon you can't actually break
down in your gut you can't if you're a
cow but you can as a human and so that
goes out so really of those thousand you
actually only absorb 900 ha and this is
what I was referring to earlier when I
said the calories in your food or on
your label are not the same as calories
in your belly it's because the
composition of food now the fat on the
other hand there's not much fiber in
there basically zero and so of those
thousand you're gonna absorb a thousand
this is how eating high quality foods
particularly foods that are high in
fiber or just foods that are really
complex and hard like carrots right
you're not gonna be able to extract
everything out of the carrot corn you
see this all the time right and so even
though a thousand calories are coming in
quote-unquote you would be in a hypo
caloric state with the carrots because
you're not actually getting all thousand
out of that you have other issues of
digestion but basically fat is very
simple and doesn't require very much
energy to digest a store where items
like a carrot and the thing here is the
physical structure it's physically dense
it takes a long time protein meat non
predigested things are much more
difficult and take more energy to break
down because of their various
composition so here's these in the
analogy of the example I would give you
since I really appreciate all the
support you give me on my patreon
account and for watching this videos
what I'm going to do is anybody that
shares this video and tags me in it and
their social media or on our YouTube I'm
gonna give $1000 to you and I will pay
you by sending you 10 $100 bills
it's gonna look just like that beautiful
crisp Franklin's good Benny Franks right
well actually half of you I'm gonna do
that too
so have you get a thousand won you get
10 $1 bills and then half you get $1,000
as well don't worry you take care of you
all daddy's got you at dawn but in this
case you're gonna get 5 $100 American
bills and you're gonna get five $100
Monopoly bills
it's a thousand either way right well
yes kind of but half of this one isn't
usable and so it's not that the money
doesn't matter it's you do have to
factor in how much you can actually use
and so instead of being all happy like
the baby here you probably now just went
like that all right this is really fiber
in this case the monopoly money would be
the fiber all right so you have to
factor that stuff in as well and you're
trying to understand energy balance the
other big thing is called a thermal
effect of food now this has been
abbreviated as TEF throughout the entire
presentation so far and what I've
actually done is I've out of protein as
well all right and this is what about a
thousand calories would be 18 ounces of
steak and I know that there's fat in
there too and I'm just trying to show
you the macro nutrients right fat
protein carbohydrate all equated for
total calories here's what we understand
it takes a tremendous amount of energy
in your belly in your body to break down
fat in fact it takes about 20 to 30
percent of the calories in the food item
to break it down so if you ingested a
thousand calories of protein you would
burn two to three hundred calories just
digesting it it's a very very high
thermal effect now fat it's not very
high notes basically zero couple percent
carbohydrate it can be high can be low
look you're not gonna have a very high
thermal effect of breaking down a piece
of bread but for something more complex
like broccoli or carrots or things like
that you're gonna burn a significant
amount of those of those calories just
breaking it down it's got a decently
high thermal effect so this again
further explains why a thousand calories
of high quality food is gonna probably
lead to more fat loss than a thousand
calories of low quality food right but
calories still matter right it's helping
you get into a negative caloric balance
and I really like this post by mental a
Handelsman you can check out his social
media page in bodybuilding it's great
stuff I want to give him a shout out
because it's a very very good
we'll see a topo alikum and when he
goodies he highlighted his paper you can
see the study in the bottom corner if
you want to read more about it but what
the study did is they put two groups of
people on the exact same calorie diet or
the exact same calorie meal 730 calories
one of them was a high highly processed
low quality food and the one was a whole
food not higher higher quality well what
happened was the low quality food had a
thermal effect of about 10% so they
burned about 73 calories digesting and
breaking down that 730 calories the
other group had a thermal effect twice
that 20% and so this is again
highlighting that point that often times
I'll grant you just emphasizing quality
will take care of quantity but that
doesn't mean quantity it doesn't matter
just like I talked about the very
beginning with that friend at the
CrossFit gym that I helped out I had a
conversation with maybe you do only need
to emphasize quality but you still
didn't recognize quantity matters but
maybe quality helps you get to a better
quantity and that's all it's doing right
the last one here is satiety this is
your sensation a full well it turns out
protein is by far the most satiating
macronutrient and this is one of the
many reasons why if people are
particularly concerned with losing fat
it's very advantageous to increase
protein now that sounds kind of
counterintuitive right but that's right
if you want to lose fat go up in protein
has that higher thermal effect and it
makes you feel full you should not be
feeling hungry all the time when you're
trying to lose weight you're doing it
wrong
if you're eating a lot of vegetable and
a lot of protein you should feel plenty
satiated and be able to get to that
caloric balance you're looking for now
fat actually has a reasonable satiating
effect carbohydrate not much all right
but if you get a good high fat high
protein meal you'll feel very full for a
long time if you eat a big carbohydrate
bolus you won't easy example you got
about the same amount of calories in a
slice of bread as you do an egg but I
promise you if you cut out your slice of
toast for breakfast in the morning you
wouldn't feel that different satiated
wise but you wouldn't know
it's a difference in how hungry you feel
feel a couple of hours later if you cut
out an egg right so the satiating effect
of protein and fat it is very very high
I wanted to add a little bit more color
to this vegetable thing and give you
some other reasons so people know you
should eat vegetables because the
vitamins and minerals and all that of
stuff but people often don't realize the
final chemicals so these are really
really important as well and they're
generally only received in the form of
vegetable you can get them from some
other places but this is really the main
source so what final chemicals do is
unlike a mineral or a nutrient where
you'll die without vitamin a you'll die
without em egg Newseum or selenium right
you have to have this I have to have
phytochemicals but they do dramatically
increase quality of life specifically
things like your immune system getting
sick or not getting sick a lot
phytochemicals are very very helpful for
that and so I want to show you what a
comparison would look like here so what
I did is we won't go through some of the
energy information with a box of mac and
cheese versus broccoli now I make my
class through this and I'd love for you
to think about this in your own how many
of you think you could or maybe have
eaten an entire box of mac and cheese in
a single setting I know I have right now
some of you may be the whole thing of
broccoli like that maybe but not many
people have done that right well if you
look at the caloric expenditure
balance here obviously there's far fewer
calories in that broccoli so this allows
you to do one of two things whatever
you'd like either you get to eat the
broccoli and have a six of the calorie
helped you this way or you get to eat
six times as much food if you eat
different food right so you can eat six
look things of broccoli actually and
meet the same amount of calories and be
way full now some of you that raised
your hand that sudden you eat a whole
thing of mac and cheese before I bet you
haven't eaten six things of broccoli
right especially for all like that and
if we start cruising down the profiles
here
some of the things that start to jump
out Oh sir look at that look at that
potassium folks it's 11 and a half grams
of potassium and that much broccoli you
can hold that as a big huge horse pill
in your hand right carbohydrates but
look at look at file oh look at all that
fiber all we have to do then since we
weren't counting for that earlier and
there's virtually no fiber and mac in
mac and cheese but there's a lot of
fiber in our 1,200 if you actually
wanted to equate this for calories you
would have to go back and add a seventh
thing of broccoli all right we're not
gonna do that we're just gonna keep
cruising on now protein of course is a
lot higher in the broccoli we all know
that the bioavailability of protein and
broccoli is not high so you now wouldn't
probably get all those 100 but it's
gonna be a lot more as the point vitamin
a 10 times the amount vitamin C five and
a half grams versus none right that's
huge amounts of vitamin C calcium six
times as much iron five times as much
now I know you're not gonna eat seven
things abraca lee or six things or raw
broccoli but maybe you have the culinary
skills to take broccoli and cut it up
doesn't have to be pretty even know that
just cut it up can you do that can you
turn a pan on medium heat don't go high
never ruin it meeting me be meeting low
great splash a little olive oil in there
get a slab of meat cut it up doesn't
have to be great don't know what you
have to do you take those things throw
those in there heat them all up and you
can get something like that all right so
this would be a very satiating very
filling
fairly tasty meal and it would be a
third of the calories or you can eat
three times the amount however you want
to look at it help if you wanted to eat
that amount and then sprinkle a little
bit of sour cream on it or some cheese
or something like that you would be very
ciated to feel very good it would be
very tasty add some hot sauce if you're
me and you still beat half the calories
right so getting to a deficit is very
reasonable without you know having to
eat spinach all day oh boy talk about
spinach you want to talk about
calorically sparse foods
one of the major reasons why vegetables
are so important for people trying to
lose weight is they haven't virtually no
calories in them you could get a giant
family size thing of lettuce or kale or
and it's like a hundred calories it is
unfortunately nothing carrots have
virtually no calories in them don't
worry about what the nonsense people
tell you about that there's too much
sugar in carrots the glycemic load is
tremendously low there's very few
calories in them you could eat boatloads
of calories feel full feel like you're
eating all the time and still be at a
very low calorie intake you can't do
that with other foods all right so this
is why vegetables are very very helpful
in managing a proper energy balance all
right so it's a summarized here do
calories matter yes of course they
matter but I will grant you is it's not
the way most people think right so
focusing on quality in other words and
here's this here's the secret I'll tell
you just don't tell anybody
don't let anybody admit this I'm not
even opposed to you telling people that
calories don't matter cuz sometimes it
has the net approach of getting them to
focus on quality more which means they
end up eating better foods like animals
vegetables fruits whole foods things
like that just like the story I told you
the beginning of the time but
information and accuracy is important
right so we do want we don't want people
to have the incorrect idea here because
sometimes it's just that net effect is
more affected and then that effect of
focusing on quality is more effective
than focusing on number and so it
provides the illusion that calories
don't matter when in fact they do but
your system of eating higher quality
foods allowed it and made it much easier
for you to be in a negative calorie
balance if that's the goal so we sort of
wrapped up all these things hopefully
that was helpful
there's a lot more to conversation I
know but hopefully you learned some
different things there now what's
interesting amount this is a
people will will sort of move the
goalposts if you will at the argument so
a lot of people will talk about things
like hey this food and I'm not gonna
name any names here so I'm pausing a
little bit cuz I don't want to give them
free shout outs but I've heard very
prominent people and very prominent
podcast talk about things like well
counties don't matter at all because you
know you could add untold amounts of
calories to something but you would
never do that right and what I'm getting
at here is the last point we do
recognize that calories do influence
behavior state ID but that's moving the
goalposts right that's what we prefer
that in logic so just because something
has a behavioral approach that doesn't
mean it's not true right so calories do
matter how it influence behavior is a
way to manipulate the calories so that's
the same thing what you're saying then
is you're agreeing you're acknowledging
that calories do matter you're just
saying your approach it makes people
feel more full so they don't eat as much
so it's an easier way to get to an Ergo
calorie balance
it's not proof that calories don't
matter in fact it is proof they do
matter is the exact opposite of what
they're trying to argue I almost don't
want them to see that cuz I feel like
when they're gonna see this video that
part they're gonna be like ah okay
I didn't realize that fundamental thing
that my evidence is actually arguing
against me the whole time now if you
want to know more about physiology I try
to keep this about energy balance it was
about fat loss of course because that's
a big part of the conversation but if
you want to know the specifics of fat
loss you can go to my website or check
out the other video I have a 55 minute
fat loss video as well as a five-minute
one so those of you with shorter
attention spans or just want to catch
the gist of it and if you learn
something this video you'll probably
learn a lot in that physiology of fat
video so you can check that out
on my youtube channel andy gallopin or
on any galco.com
that's up and it available for you but I
did want to end on a couple of practical
tips and talk about some things of what
to do alright so the first thing is
caloric balance now unlike most people
one of the big mistakes that gets made
is you change calorie
too much what the research shows right
now whether you're trying to gain muscle
or lose fat as you don't want to
manipulate calorie balance by more than
10 to 15 percent so if you're trying to
add muscle and you go up by more than 15
percent and anyone has done this knows
exactly what I'm talking about it's
actually not sustainable you feel
terrible you get sick you don't feel
like eating and it's really really hard
to do that in addition if you add more
than 10 or so percent in calories you
might continue to gain weight but a
higher percentage of that weight will
start coming from fat so if you're
interested in gaining the absolute
highest amount of weight possible well
then eat as many calories as you can get
away with but if you want to gain as
much muscle as you can and not gain a
lot of fat don't go more than 10 or 15
percent now for fat loss it's the other
side of the equation here same thing the
evidence is pretty clear that the most
the people who have the most success
with losing weight and keeping it off
for the longest are those that only
reduce calorie intake by 10 or so
percent tell me much more than that
if you crash too much you end up being
in that evolutionary biology issue of
maybe shutting down eat too much so be
careful there so the way I like to do
that is by having a tremendous amount of
veggies I've talked about why that's
important earlier have some fat have
some protein like I said try to go up on
protein it's very fulfilling and has a
high thermal effect focused on real food
that helps actually accomplish all the
things I said before and regulate liquid
calories a lot of times people that have
struggled with weight loss is because
they're struggling with having a lot of
extra calories in their food that they
didn't realize were there because
they're drinking calories which are not
satiating and don't have fiber make sure
your approach like I said associating
and sustainable this is about a long
term behavioral win of course you're
hopefully aware that diets are not good
lifestyle changes are a lot more
effective so this is something you want
to do for the long term and they
approach the 99 year rule is be consist
so you can't do everything that I
recommend doing for especially fat loss
so I would say shoot for 80 90 percent
if you can do 90 percent of what I
recommend 90 percent of the time you'll
be in a really really good spot and then
the last one of course is patience right
you got to give yourself some time it's
a slow process that is far more
physiologically sustainable than
crashing and I can show you some
evidence here this is my own body weight
getting ready for a national
championships one year and I had to go
for me as you can see about 178 pounds
all the way down to 151 which I did and
performed great what's interesting about
this graph let's take a look at things
like that I mean that's a chunk of about
six weeks where as i zoom in I didn't do
anything
weight loss once I pretty much stayed on
my diet I was doing great I was hungry a
little bit you know not that perfect
amount but not much I was at a caloric
deficit but I wasn't really losing
weight and so this can kind of fool you
if I zoomed in on this six weeks I would
think my diet isn't working at all but
if I zoomed out on the whole thing it
actually looks like I lost weight the
entire time so this is all a function of
how zoomed in or zoomed out on that
calendar you are so if you're getting
really frustrated with a diet it's not
working I want ask yourself what do you
think you're at right now you might be
zoomed in on one of those short
month-long spans or something where you
might put it to a little bit but I want
you to have that perspective of zooming
out and go what do you think if I keep
on this routine if I keep doing well do
I really think I won't lose weight for
the next year of course you will all
right so just be patient you'll get
there and this also allows you to have
days like this right or like that
there's gonna be some birthday trips to
Vegas there's gonna be some holidays and
other things like that
live life you're gonna want to do that
right don't ruin your life to lose a
little bit of weight you have to make
some sacrifice but we still want to make
room for for life in there
right so a couple of last thoughts
ignoramus this is something I live by as
a scientist I've committed to it I have
to willingly admit we already way past
our 55-minute I'm here right which means
I had to omit a lot of things so no I
did not cover everything you ever need
to know about energy balance there is a
lot of other stuff involved of course
hormones play a role but there is no
magic as assumed my colleagues call it
insulin fairy right that's been
extremely well documented but does that
mean it doesn't matter at all no of
course it matters and it plays a very
important role
happiness dopamine serotonin all these
things play a role and there's all all
kinds of other factors that go on the
equation that we didn't get to right and
that was just a function of time so I am
aware of a lot of them I'm sure there's
plenty of things I don't know and this
so this is very funny we also have to
consider context right
there's a lot of other things that go
into people making dietary decisions
even about calories skin care gut health
religious purposes cultural practices
all that are important pieces of the
puzzle that influence say energy balance
that I didn't have time to get to mood
recovery all that stuff right trying to
maximize performance and so those are
the things that context come into play
and that will always be true so what's
absolutely true in one context could be
completely false in another context and
vice-versa so we do want to recognize
this is not the end-all be-all
but hopefully you did learn something I
would encourage you to check this out
this is from the International Society
of sports nutrition Allen Aragon and
Joey Antonio Joey's organization Allen
Aragon read the paper but this is
fantastic it is their position stand on
diets and body composition so if you
want to learn about all the different
diets what's the evidence say for all
these diets and how effective they are
for fat loss this is the best place to
go and has all of that research
summarized for you it's actually pretty
easy to read even for non scientists and
again good on the ISSN for making this
open access which means it's free anyone
can look at it it's not behind
you don't have to have a school email
address or login just google the title
it's up on their website you'll find it
immediately so a very very good resource
if you want to read more about what some
specific diets how effective some of
them are or not that's all in there so
that being said thanks a lot for joining
me again I appreciate the support as
always I would really really appreciate
it
if you shared this stuff around on your
youtube again or your social media tag
me help me spread the word obviously
this takes me a tremendous amount of
time to put these things together and
it's a culmination of years of research
and so that's a lot of money and a lot
of time that goes into these things so I
don't ask for much for you just a little
bit of help sharing things around if you
enjoyed this if you hate if you can
afford it I would also appreciate going
to my patreon account so www.payoor.com
for slash Andy Galvin and kicking in a
buck or two or buying me a virtual cup
of coffee that way you'll notice I don't
take a penny that for my own profit but
what I want to do in fact I have just
recently hired somebody with the money
that people have donated to put together
study questions for these videos I also
some blog notes and a short write-up so
maybe you'll actually find out that you
like just reading the write-up rather
than watch some videos as much but
that's how I actually do this thing so I
can't afford to do any of those those
things on my own and because it's a lot
and it's a lot of work and I have to
have people help me with these things so
that's directly where that money goes so
I really appreciate any contribution you
can make to that and we'll help moving
this forward if you can't afford it cool
just keep loving it keep learning it
keep getting better and keep making the
world a better place
share it if you can if you don't have
social media or anywhere else to share
it just enjoy it and make your life
better that's good enough for me so I'll
keep being this productive as I can
based on how much support I can get but
if not I will catch you next time and I
really appreciate it